Guide to the John Browne, Commonplace Book
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Osborn fb155 (Volume 1)
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - "A Table of the several revenues and tenths of every Bishopric in England and Wales" (Volume 1)
      Autograph MS [c.17th century].
      p.356-357.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Notes concerning proceedings in Chancery], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      The jurisdiction of the Court of
      Chancery in cases of equity and
      conscience. Citations of statutes
      and arguments.
      p.358-361.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - "Some queries and resolutions concerning the course of the convocation" (Volume 1)
      Autograph MS.
      Ten questions and answers, including
      how convocation is summoned and
      dismissed, the membership, etc.
      p.361-363.
  - LOUIS XIV, KING OF FRANCE, 1638-1715
    - [Letters to the Pope and to certain cardinals, 1662 Aug 30] (Volume 1)
      Complains of the attack on his
      ambassador by the Pope's soldiers in
      the streets of Rome and demands
      satisfaction. Pope Alexander VII
      (1599-1667); Charles de Blanchefort,
      duc de Crequy (1623-1687). See p.385
      for another copy.
      p.364-365.
  - MIDDLESEX, LIONEL CRANFIELD, 3RD EARL OF, 1625-1674
    - [Challenge to a duel sent to John Egerton, 2nd earl of Bridgewater (1622-1686), 1633] (Volume 1)
      p.366.
  - STRAFFORD, THOMAS WENTWORTH, 1ST EARL OF, 1593-1641
    - [Proposition sent to the King for securing his Majesty's estate for the bridling of Parliament, and for the increase of revenue] (Volume 1)
      Proposals to fortify the Kingdom,
      limit the power of Parliament,
      impose yearly taxes, etc. Published
      in 1646 with title, Straffords Plot
      Discovered. This treatise was
      written by Sir Robert Dudley
      (1574-1649) in 1614, and in 1630 was
      used as evidence in a Star Chamber
      suit against Sir Robert Cotton (see
      p.463-470).
      p.367-378.
  - RALEIGH, SIR WALTER, 1552?-1618
    - [Letter to King James I, 1618 Oct], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Letter sent "a little before his
      death." A defense of his actions
      and a protestation of his loyalty.
      p.379-380.
  - RALEIGH, SIR WALTER, 1552?-1618
    - [His Protestation at his death, 1618 Oct], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Denies the accusations made against
      him.
      p.381-382.
  - SHELDON, GILBERT, ABP. OF CANTERBURY, 1598-1677
    - [Letter to Humphrey Henchman, bp. of London (1592-1675), to be communicated to all the Bishops of his province, 1669 June 8] (Volume 1)
      On suppressing conventicles.
      p.382-383.
  - HENCHMAN, HUMPHREY, BP. OF LONDON, 1592-1675
    - [Letter to Joseph Henshaw, Bp. of Peterborough (1603-1679), 1669 June 20, and the Archdeacons Instructions, 1669 July 7] (Volume 1)
      Letters on suppressing conventicles
      followed by instructions on the same.
      p.383-384.
  - LOUIS XIV, KING OF FRANCE, 1638-1715
    - [Letter to the Pope, 1662 Aug 30], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      In English.
      Another copy of letter on p.364.
      p.385
  - RUVIGNY AND RAINEVAL, HENRI, MARQUIS OF, 1648-1720
    - [A paper brought into the House of Lords from the French Ambassador, 1673/4 Jan 25], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      On the alliance between France and
      England and the war against the
      Dutch.
      p.386-401.
  - MONMOUTH, JAMES SCOTT, DUKE OF, 1649-1685
    - [Letter to the Vice Chancellor of Cambridge University, 1674 Oct], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Orders the clergy to reform their
      hairstyles and their manner of
      preaching.
      p.401-402.
  - GREAT BRITAIN TREATIES (CHARLES II, 1660-1685)
    - "The heads of the Articles between the King of Great Britain and the States of the United Provinces, 1673" (Volume 1)
      Peace treaty; includes "Private
      Articles" of peace between England
      and Holland.
      p.402-405.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "A Petition to the Queen for Association in Religion", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      14 p.
      MS copy c. 1584.
      Recommends an oath for the defense
      of the Queen and the Protestant
      religion. Includes comments on
      various religious groups.
      p.405-418.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Petition to the Archbishops and Bishops, c.1602] (Volume 1)
      16 p.
      Argues against the toleration of
      Catholics and maintains that
      dangerous Catholics are being favored
      while loyal Puritans are suffering.
      p.419-434.
  - LUZANCY, MONSIEUR DE
    - [Statement of his case against St. Germain, 1675 Oct], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      The case of M. de Luzancy, a French
      Preacher "newly converted" to
      Protestantism, against a French
      Jesuit who tried to re-convert him.
      The case was debated in the Commons,
      1675 Nov 8. CJ, ix, 369, 375.
      p.435-439.
  - MANCHESTER, HENRY MONTAGU, 1ST EARL OF, 1563?-1642
    - [Letter to his son, Walter Montagu (1603-1677), concerning his son's conversion to Catholicism, 1635], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Printed in 1641.
      p.440-449.
  - LUCAS, JOHN LUCAS, 1ST BARON OF, 1606-1671
    - [Speech in the House of Lords against granting a large subsidy to the King, 1669/70 Feb 22], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Cobbett, v.4, 473.
      p.450-453.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 2ND DUKE OF, 1628-87
    - [Speech in the House of Lords favoring a Bill of Indulgence for Protestant dissenters, 1675 Oct] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Cobbett, v.4, 789.
      p.453-454.
  - SHAFTESBURY, ANTHONY ASHLEY COOPER, 1ST EARL OF, 1621-1683
    - [Letter to Charles Howard, 1st earl of Carlisle (1629-1685), 1675 Feb 3], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      On the necessity of calling a new
      Parliament and his refusal to accept
      office until one is called. Printed
      in Brown, The First Earl of
      Shaftesbury, p. 277.
      p.455-456.
  - [GREAT BRITAIN EXCHEQUER]
    - "Retrenchment of the King's expences" [c. later 17th century], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      List of the reduction in the
      allowances of departments such as
      the Household, Privy Purse, Secret
      Service, etc.
      p.456.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Commission to Thomas Howard, 2nd earl of Arundel (1585-1646), to be general of the army to be sent to the North, 1638] (Volume 1)
      p.457-460.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. COURT OF THE LORD HIGH STEWARD
    - "The names of the peers in commission upon the trial of Lord Cornwallis, 1678 June 30", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      List of the peers who tried Charles
      Cornwallis, 3rd baron of Cornwallis
      (1655-1698), for manslaughter.
      p.460-461.
  - SHAFTESBURY, ANTHONY ASHLEY COOPER, 1ST EARL OF, 1621-1683
    - "The Substance of the Earl of Shaftesbury's Speech in the Court of Kings Bench, when he was brought thither by Habeas Corpus" [1677 June 29] (Volume 1)
      Challenges the right of the House of
      Lords to imprison him indefinitely.
      Printed in 1679.
      p.461-463.
  - HEATH, SIR ROBERT, 1575-1649
    - [The Attorney General's information against Sir Robert Cotton and others, 1629] (Volume 1)
      Recommendation that Sir Robert Bruce
      Cotton, bart. (1571-1631), and others
      be proceeded against in Star Chamber
      for circulating a slanderous treatise
      harmful to the King. The content of
      the treatise, "A Proposition for his
      Majesty's service to bridle the
      Impertinency of Parliaments", is
      given by Sir Robert Dudley. See
      p.367-378, where the same treatise is
      attributed to the Earl of Strafford.
      p.463-470.
  - SCOTLAND.
    - [The Scots' reasons against the Book of Common Prayer, 1637 Aug], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Objects to the Prayer Book as Popish
      and full of errors.
      p.470-472.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "A Narrative of the Life of John Packer, Esq.", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Anonymous MS copy.
      Account of Packer's career and good
      works (1572-1649).
      p.472-477.
  - ABBOT, GEORGE, ABP. OF CANTERBURY, 1582-1633
    - [Petition to the King against granting toleration to Roman Catholics, c.1624], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. The petition is dated 1663
      and attributed to Gilbert Sheldon,
      Abp. of Canterbury (1598-1677), but
      in Rushworth, I, 85, the petition is
      attributed to Abbot. The DNB article
      on Abbot mentions this petition and
      claims it was a forgery.
      p.478.
  - USSHER, JAMES ABP. OF ARMAGH, 1581-1656
    - [Petition of the Irish bishops against Popery, 1626 Nov 26], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Signed by Ussher and 11 other
      bishops.
      p.479.
  - WIGORN, JOHN
    - [Statement of religious controversies c. 17th century], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Criticizes those who "toss to and
      fro" in religion.
      p.480.
  - SHAFTESBURY, ANTHONY ASHLEY COOPER, 1ST EARL OF, 1621-1683
    - "A Speech lately made by a noble Peere of the Realme in Parliament 1681", [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      The speech was never actually given
      in Parliament. Printed in 1681 and
      in Cobbett, v.4, cxi. Shaftesbury
      advocates withholding supplies until
      the King satisfies the people about
      the succession of the Duke of York.
      p.481-485.
  - [PRESBYTERIANS IN ENGLAND]
    - [Address of the Presbyterian ministers of London to the King, 1687 April 30] (Volume 1)
      Thanks to the King for his
      Declaration for liberty of
      conscience.
      p.486.
  - FRIENDS, SOCIETY OF
    - [Address to the King, 1687], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      conscience. p.486-487.
  - JAMES II, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1633-1701
    - "His Majesties gracious declaration to all his Loving Subjects for Liberty of conscience" [1687 April 4], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Printed in 1687.
      p.488-491.
  - ROCHESTER, JOHN WILMOT, 2ND EARL OF, 1647-1680
    - [Letter to Dr Burnet, 1680 June 25], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Deathbed letter of repentance to
      Gilbert Burnet, bp. of Salisbury
      (1643-1715) Published in 1680.
      p.492.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1663. HOUSE OF COMMONS
    - [Address to the King against toleration, 1662/3 Feb 27], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      MS copy. CJ, VIII, 442.
      p.493-495.
  - ARRUNDELL, THOMAS
    - [Petition to the House of Lords asking for relief for Catholics, 1661 June 10], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Signed by Arundell and five others.
      LJ, xi, 276.
      p.496.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Extracts from the records of Parliament concerning Catholics, 1661 June 11-28], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Orders of the House, list of penal
      laws, and debates concerning
      Catholics.
      p.497-498 and 516-519.
  - ESSEX, ARTHUR CAPEL, 1ST EARL OF, 1631-1685
    - [Speech and petition to the King. 1680/1 Jan 25] (Volume 1)
      Signed by Essex and 15 other peers
      who opposed the calling of Parliament
      to Oxford. Cobbett, v.4, 1297.
      p.499-501.
  - POVEY, MERCY
    - "A Letter to Staffordshire occasioned by the dissenters complaint of their Persecution" [c.1685], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Criticizes dissenters who complain of
      their persecution.
      p.502-505.
  - FAGEL, GASPER, 1629-1688
    - "A letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel, pensioner of Holland, to Mr. James Stewart, Advocate, giving an account of the Prince and Princess of Orange's thoughts concerning the repeal of the Test, and the Penal Laws" 1687 Nov 4 (Volume 1)
      MS copy. Published in London, 1688.
      Sir James Stewart (1635-1715)
      William III, King of Great Britain
      (1650-1702); Mary II, Queen of Great
      Britain (1662-1694).
      p.506-512.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "A letter written by a Jesuit at London to the College at Liege, intercepted and carried to the Prince of Orange" [1688/9 Feb 2] (Volume 1)
      On the favor shown to Jesuits by King
      James II. A version printed in 1688.
      p.513-515.
  - PETRE, EDWARD, 1631-1699
    - [Letter to Father Francois d'Aix La Chaise (1627-1709)] c.1688, [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      On affairs in England. Printed in
      1688.
      p.520-525.
  - PARTRIDGE, JOHN, 1644-1715
    - "Judicium Astrologicum pro Anno 1688" [1687], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Astrological notes on political
      events. Printed in 1689 under title
      "Annus Mirabilis or Strange and
      Wonderful Predictions and
      Observations Gathered out of
      Mr.J.Partidges Almanack."
      p.527-537.
  - LA CHAISE, FRANCOIS D'AIX, 1627-1709
    - "Father La Chaise's Project for the Extirpation of Hereticks in a letter from him to Father Peters" [1688 July 8], [n.d.] (Volume 1)
      Advice to Edward Petre (1631-1699) on
      rooting out heretics in England and
      an account of his own actions in
      France. Printed in 1688.
      p.539-543.